眼前这个潦草的三，只有二十八乘二十八个像素。可不管它怎么歪、怎么糊，我们的大脑几乎一眼就能认出来。
This messy three has only twenty-eight by twenty-eight pixels, yet our brains recognize it instantly despite its variations.
问题是，换成程序就没这么简单。不同写法的像素值差别很大，机器却要判断它们表达的是同一个数字。
For a program, the task is harder: the pixel values vary widely, but the machine must identify the same digit.
把一张二十八乘二十八的灰度图交给程序，再要求它从零到九里选出答案，这就是机器学习最经典的入门问题。
Giving a twenty-eight by twenty-eight grayscale image to a program and asking it to choose a digit from zero to nine is a classic machine-learning problem.
这一期不讲营销词，也先不钻进复杂公式。我们只做一件事：看清神经网络的结构，到底怎样把图像变成判断。
This episode skips buzzwords and heavy formulas, focusing on how a neural network turns an image into a decision.
接下来搭建的是最基础的一类网络。它不代表今天最强的模型，却保留了理解深度学习所需的核心骨架。
We will build a basic network. It is not today's strongest model, but it contains the core structure needed to understand deep learning.
神经网络的变体很多，但先把它想成一组会保存数字的节点。节点彼此连接，数字就在连接中一层层传递。
There are many neural-network variants, but start by seeing it as nodes that store numbers and pass them through layers of connections.
输入图像有二十八乘二十八个像素，也就是七百八十四个输入节点。每个节点只记录对应像素有多亮。
The image has twenty-eight by twenty-eight pixels, or seven hundred eighty-four input nodes. Each node records the brightness of one pixel.
黑色可以看作零，白色可以看作一，中间是不同灰度。节点里的这个数，叫作激活值；数越大，画面里的节点就越亮。
Black can be treated as zero and white as one, with gray in between. This number is the activation, and a larger value lights the node more brightly.
最右边的输出层只有十个节点，分别代表零到九。谁的激活值最高，网络就认为这张图最像哪个数字。
The output layer has only ten nodes, one for each digit. The node with the highest activation is the network's chosen digit.
输入层和输出层之间，还有隐藏层。它们不直接告诉你答案，却负责把最原始的像素信息，逐步组合成更有意义的特征。
Between input and output are hidden layers. They do not state the answer directly; they turn raw pixels into increasingly meaningful features.
在这套示例网络里，信息从左向右流动：每一层的激活值，会共同决定下一层哪些节点被点亮。
In this example network, information flows from left to right: activations in one layer jointly determine which nodes light up in the next.
当一张数字图像输入后，七百八十四个像素同时变成激活值。它们经过隐藏层，最后让某个输出节点最亮，于是得到分类结果。
When an image enters, its seven hundred eighty-four pixels become activations, pass through hidden layers, and ultimately make one output node brightest.
为什么分层会有用？因为人识别数字时，也不是死记每个像素，而是在看圆环、竖线、斜线这些局部结构。
Why do layers help? Humans do not memorize every pixel; we notice local structures such as loops, vertical strokes, and diagonal strokes.
理想情况下，某些隐藏节点会对顶部圆环敏感，另一些节点会识别右侧竖线。后面的层再把这些零件组合起来。
Ideally, some hidden nodes respond to an upper loop and others to a right-side line, while later layers combine these parts.
不过，网络并不是由人手工规定每个节点该看什么。真正关键的问题是：它怎样从数据里学会这些连接规则？
However, people do not manually assign what each node should detect. The key question is how the network learns connection rules from data.
先从最简单的一条连接看起。前一层一个节点的激活值，要怎样影响下一层某个节点？答案藏在权重里。
Start with one connection: how does one activation influence a node in the next layer? The answer lies in its weight.
权重可以理解为这条连接的重要程度。正权重会推动下一个节点变亮，负权重则会压低它的激活。
A weight represents the importance of a connection. A positive weight pushes the next node brighter, while a negative weight suppresses it.
一个节点不会只听一条线的意见。它会收集前一层所有连接传来的信号，按各自权重加总，形成一个初步结果。
A node does not listen to just one connection. It gathers signals from all nodes in the previous layer and adds them according to their weights.
但加总还不够。网络还会加入一个偏置值，相当于给节点设置基础门槛，让它不会只因一点微弱信号就轻易响应。
But summing is not enough. The network adds a bias, like a baseline threshold that prevents a node from responding to weak evidence alone.
加权和再经过激活函数，才会变成新的激活值。这里使用的是 sigmoid 函数，它把任意大小的结果压缩到零和一之间。
The weighted sum then passes through an activation function to become a new activation. Here sigmoid compresses any value into the range from zero to one.
所以一层网络的计算，可以浓缩成四步：接收输入，乘上权重，加入偏置，最后经过激活函数输出。
A layer's computation can be summarized in four steps: receive inputs, apply weights, add a bias, and pass the result through an activation function.
这些数一旦确定，整张图像的去向也就确定了。不同的权重和偏置，会让网络对同一幅图给出完全不同的判断。
Once these values are fixed, the image's path is fixed too. Different weights and biases can make the same picture receive a completely different judgment.
训练的本质，就是不断调整这些参数。让正确数字对应的输出越来越高，让错误数字的输出逐渐降低。
Training is the process of repeatedly adjusting these parameters, raising the output for the correct digit and lowering outputs for wrong ones.
从这个角度看，神经网络不是神秘黑箱。它只是一个参数很多、层数很多，但每一步规则都明确的计算系统。
From this perspective, a neural network is not a mysterious black box. It is a computation system with many parameters and layers, but clear rules at every step.
当然，单个权重的意义未必直观。真正的能力来自大量节点和连接共同形成的模式，而不是某一条线单独决定答案。
A single weight may not be intuitive. The network's ability comes from patterns formed by many nodes and connections, not from one line deciding the answer.
理解权重和偏置，仍然很重要。它能让我们在模型出错时知道该从哪里检查，也能帮助我们理解模型为什么会做出某种判断。
Understanding weights and biases still matters. It gives us a place to inspect when a model fails and helps explain why it makes a decision.
当节点和连接数量越来越多，逐条写公式会变得笨重。于是我们用向量装下一层的所有激活值，用矩阵装下所有权重。
As nodes and connections multiply, writing every formula becomes cumbersome. We use vectors for a layer's activations and matrices for all its weights.
矩阵的每一行，对应下一层的一个节点；它记录了这个节点从前一层所有节点接收的权重。
Each row of the matrix corresponds to one node in the next layer and records the weights it receives from every node in the previous layer.
一次矩阵乘法，就能并行算出整层节点的加权和。再加上偏置向量，经过激活函数，下一层的状态就全部得到。
One matrix multiplication computes weighted sums for a whole layer in parallel. Add the bias vector and activation function to get the entire next state.
这也是为什么线性代数是机器学习的基础语言。它把海量连接压缩成紧凑运算，让代码更简单，计算也更快。
This is why linear algebra is a foundational language for machine learning. It compresses massive connections into compact operations, making code simpler and computation faster.
严格来说，每个神经元不只是存着一个数。面对不同输入，它更像一个函数：接收上一层的输出，再给出零到一之间的新结果。
Strictly speaking, each neuron is more than a stored number. For different inputs, it acts like a function that receives prior outputs and produces a new value between zero and one.
整张网络也是一个函数。它接收七百八十四个输入数字，经过多次矩阵运算和激活，最后输出十个数字的判断。
The entire network is also a function. It receives seven hundred eighty-four input values, performs repeated matrix operations and activations, then outputs ten values.
这个示例网络大约有一万三千个参数。复杂并不是缺点，因为只有足够灵活的函数，才有机会适应千差万别的手写数字。
This example network has about thirteen thousand parameters. Complexity is not a flaw, because a flexible enough function can adapt to diverse handwritten digits.
至于这些权重和偏置究竟怎样从训练数据里学出来，那是下一步要解决的问题。先记住，网络的结构已经把学习的舞台搭好了。
How weights and biases are learned from training data is the next question. For now, remember that the network's structure has set the stage for learning.
这里用的 sigmoid，是早期神经网络常见的激活函数。它把结果挤进零到一之间，便于用亮暗来表示节点的响应程度。
The sigmoid used here was common in early neural networks. It squeezes results into zero to one, making activation easy to visualize as brightness.
但现代深层网络常用 ReLU 等函数，因为它们通常更容易训练。模型在变，核心逻辑不变：输入经过参数化的层层变换，最终形成判断。
Modern deep networks often use functions such as ReLU because they are usually easier to train. The core logic remains: inputs pass through parameterized transformations to form a decision.